[Music]
i want to try this out for a really long
time and today is the day i want to find
out if a mobile phone is any good for
photogrammetry here's the intro
in theory a phone should work perfectly
fine photogrammetry is creating an
object out of multiple images so the
lack of resolution from the small phone
sensor is not as big of an issue of
course that means shooting more images
and more close-ups of the object that's
the only way to compete with the clarity
of a big sensor camera for now though we
won't go overboard with the number of
photos taken we'll just focus on the
basics see what we can get out of a
phone in order to properly capture an
object surface we need a polarizing
filter on both the lens and the light
source that ensures no reflections on
the surface of the object this will
allow us to re-light the object later on
without any issues i've covered that in
a previous video so if you haven't
watched that i'll leave a link in the
description below
to help with the whole reflection
situation i'll use the relatively
diffuse objects so the reflections won't
be that obvious we'll try three objects
a pinecone this wooden stick
and this beautiful brick make no
mistakes even these diffuse objects have
reflections they're just not as visible
as shiny reflective surfaces
since we want to compare the results
i'll be shooting the objects twice once
with the iphone 11 pro and once with the
gh5 it's an older phone but it's still
able to capture a good amount of detail
of course with a newer phone the results
will be better
let's start
for lighting the object i'm going very
simple i'll take advantage of the
natural light and to fill out the
remaining shadows i'll use an led light
with neutral white balance
to reduce the harsh shadows of the sun
and make everything as soft as possible
we need a diffuser
thankfully my currents are white so
they're the ultimate light diffuser
now let's start taking some pictures
right off the bat i've hit the first
snag iphone's default lens is way too
wide for landscapes it's perfect but for
photogrammetry not so much
switching to the 2x telephoto lens
solves a problem but the quality there
is not as good
iphone's telephoto lens is not as bright
and also has a lower quality ccd so the
images won't be as good as the ones
taken with a default lens
the images will be noisier and won't
have a ton of detail but on the other
hand that's all we've got so that's what
we're going to use
the other interesting challenge was
finding a way to prop up the phone
putting the phone on a tripod would move
it too far away from the object so i
ended up using a combination of a tripod
head and some lens caps
a really professional setup but it does
a trick so i'm fine with it
my other concern was camera shake since
i can't remotely trigger the shutter i
have to manually press the button on the
screen which can result in blurry images
but this is where the decision to not
shoot with polarized light helps a lot
with plenty of natural light further
enhanced by the led light the phone
won't have to use slow shutter speeds
but if we did shoot things the proper
way i'm not exactly sure how i would be
able to compensate for camera shake
the other issue with low light
environments is that apple's night mode
gets enabled and we definitely don't
want that night mode does a lot of post
processing which compromises the quality
of the image it aggressively reduces
noise and over sharpens the image to
give the illusion of detail so it's
definitely not something we want to
introduce to our images
i've covered apple's night mode in a
previous video so i'll leave that in the
description below as well
the only way i can think of shooting
with a phone and cross polarized light
is to have multiple light sources for
adequate light but also polarizing
filters for all of these lights at that
point having spent this much money on
equipment i don't know why anyone would
use a phone for the actual shoot but
that's besides the point let's get back
to our shoot
it's very important to lock the exposure
and focus otherwise each image will be
completely different than the last one
throwing things out of whack
the process is a bit tedious but with
the rotations of the object handled
automatically it's not as bad
[Music]
now that the iphone photos are complete
it's time to shoot the same thing all
over again with the camera things are
much easier here because there's a lot
more flexibility we can use a tripod
change lenses basically set up the shot
exactly like we want to
[Music]
and with the phone cameras photos ready
it's time for some processing
a few minutes later
and here are the results
i won't tell you which is which right
away have a guess
the objects as far as overall shape goes
are identical there are some differences
in color and detail but both look really
good the left cone compared to the right
one looks like it has a blurrier texture
but that's only if you see the cone side
by side if i disable the right one and
inspect cone number one on its own the
texture feels really nice
so
which is which
cone number two the one on the right
side is the one made with the iphone and
cone number one is down with the gh5 you
might be impressed by how much detail is
on the iphone texture but this detail is
all artificial it's just the iphone
being very aggressive with sharpening
you can tell quite easily if we take a
look at the bottom of the cone if we
zoom in what looked like a lot of detail
now looks more like a posterized
aggressive sharpening
cone number one's texture feels much
more natural and on the plus side if we
want to sharpen the result we can i'll
just apply a non-sharp mask in photoshop
and now we have a really sharp result
and if we apply that to our cone we have
a sharp result that still looks way more
natural than the one from the iphone
that's the good thing with images taken
with a camera the results are very
neutral and we can fine tune them the
way we want to after the fact with a
phone we're getting a pre-decided result
that's always punchier and more
processed
in hindsight i should have used raw for
the iphone's images since no pause
processing is applied there but that
would also involve one extra step
converting the raw images to jpeg in
order to use them for photogrammetry now
let's move on to the next object
both look good as far as form goes which
is quite encouraging it means that the
images had enough detail to accurately
describe the object so judging by the
form alone it's not easy to tell which
is which if we turn on the textures
though it's quite obvious which one is
taken with the iphone and which one is
with the gh5
as with the previous object the one that
looks more detailed is the one taken
with the iphone but like before the
detail is an illusion if we zoom in
closer you will notice how much the
texture falls apart the one taking with
the gh5 object number two feels very
natural
once more the gh5s less aggressive
sharpening and higher resolution gives
better results and once we apply some
sharpening to the image we get some nice
sharp details
the other dead giveaway is the white
balance of the texture
iphones ever since i can remember always
lean into the yellow end of the spectrum
the photos taken with the gh5 have a
more correct and neutral white balance
the yellowish white balance though can
be fixed relatively easily so at least
the result in that regard can be
adjusted
no matter what though the iphone result
is quite impressive especially if we
consider the fact that a phone's primary
function is phone calls and messaging
not photogrammetry in that regard this
result is mind-blowing
and last but not least our final object
this beautifully disgusting brick
ignore this fail the scan part that was
an error on my side
i'm sure by now you can tell which model
is done with which camera number one is
done with the iphone and number two with
a gh5
here the over sharpening went a little
bit too crazy i might have also
underexposed the iphone images a tad
i'm not sure though if this is my fault
no matter what though the over
sharpening makes the model look
unrealistic
the one shot with the gh5 looks much
more natural if we compare the images
side by side you can see how aggressive
the iphone is with the sharpening
so if you're planning to shoot something
with your phone definitely shoot it with
raw and not with a default camera
this will ensure that no pause
processing is applied it will add one
extra step in the process but the
results will be infinitely
better so
what's the verdict
i would say if we take the proper steps
and ensure lots of light and raw
shooting we can get some nice looking
objects from a phone
but we definitely need to be more
careful than with an ordinary camera raw
is an absolute must in order to avoid
post processing and any other modes like
apple's night mode
cross polarization with a phone is a tad
trickier not only because of the
polarizing filter for the phone's lens
but also because of the higher noise
floor of the phone's small ccd chip
unless we have adequate lights and
filters
with newer phones i'm sure the results
will be even better iphone 13's macro
lens for example might be able to
capture a lot more detail
don't forget that more detail means
better forms and richer textures
is my iphone going to replace my camera
for photogrammetry definitely not
but it's good to know that if you're in
a pinch and you're willing to follow
some basic rules you will be able to get
some good results out of it
and that's about it for this video how
do you think the iphone fared would you
personally use your phone to do this
sort of thing let me know in the
comments below take care and i'll see
you in the next one